<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 20</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="7d405107-b468-44d7-8ccc-cac9b99491ba" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16313"/>
Full of disquietude and misgiving the Surgeon left the cabin. Was Captain Vere suddenly affected in his mind, or was it but a transient excitement, brought about by so strange a extraordinary a tragedy? As to the drum-head court, it struck the Surgeon as impolitic, if nothing more. The thing to do, he thought, was to place Billy Budd in confinement and in a way dictated by by usage, and postpone further action in so extraordinary a case, to such time as they should rejoin the squadron, and then refer it to the Admiral. He recalled the unwonted agitation of Captain Vere and his excited exclamations  <pb facs="861adc82-0b0e-471f-9ae9-b105ef551b97" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16315"/>so at variance with his normal manner. Was he unhinged? 

</p><p>But assuming that he is, it is not so susceptible of proof What then can he do? No more trying situation is conceivable than that of an officer subordinate under a Captain whom he suspects to be, not mad indeed, but yet not quite unaffected in his intellects. To argue his order to him would be insolence. To resist him would be mutiny. 

</p><p>In obedience to Captain Vere, he communicated what had happened to the lieutenants &amp; captain of marines; and saying nothing as to the Captain&apos;s state. They fully shared his own surprise and concern. <pb facs="eea0f387-3d63-4ee3-8ef2-b4d7ca78cb4f" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18563"/>Like him too they seemed to think that such a matter should be referred to the Admiral.</p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
