<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 24</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="ebef05ab-43d2-483e-9ccb-1cfdd5d128d5" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18616"/>
In a seventy-four of the old order the deck known as the upper gun-deck was the one covered over by the spar-deck which last though not without its armament was for the most part exposed to the weather. In general it was at all hours free from hammocks; those of the crew swinging on the lower gun-deck, and berth-deck, the latter being not only a dormitory but also the place for the stowing of the sailors&apos; bags, and on both sides lined with the large chests or movable pantries of the many messes of the men. <pb facs="7fdc9b79-b23a-486d-8824-655aa2e155dd" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18617"/>

</p><p>On the starboard side of the Indomitable&apos;s upper gun-deck, behold Billy Budd under sentry lying prone in irons in one of the bays formed by the regular spaceing of the guns comprising the batteries on either side. All these pieces, were of the heavier calibre of that period. Mounted on lumbering wooden carriges they were hampered with cumbersome harness of breechen and strong side-tackles for running them out. Guns and carriages, together with the long rammers and shorter lintstocks lodged in loops overhead–all these, as customary, were painted black; and the heavy hempen breechens tarred to the same tint, wore the like <pb facs="138f9b9d-d660-48c8-9746-931f525d9829" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18618"/>livery of the undertakers. In contrast with the funereal hue of these surroundings the prone sailor&apos;s exterior apparel, white jumper and white duck trousers, each more or less soiled, dimly glimmered in the  obscure light of the bay like a patch of discolored snow in early April lingering at some upland cave&apos;s black mouth. In effect he is already in his shroud or the garments that shall serve him in lieu of one. Over him but scarce illuminating him, two battle-lanterns swing from two massive beams of the deck above. Fed with the oil supplied by the war-contracters (whose gains, honest or otherwise, are in every land an anticipated portion of the harvest of death) with <pb facs="3abc0ab3-0051-40e8-ae41-e3292e60abc5" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18619"/>flickering splashes of dirty yellow light they pollute the pale moonshine all but ineffectually struggling in obstructed flecks thro the open ports from which the tompioned cannon protrude. Other lanterns at intervals serve but to bring out somewhat the obscurer bays which like small confessionals or side-chapels in a cathedral branch from the long dim-vistaed broad-aisle between the two batteries of that covered tier.  

</p><p>Such was the deck where now lay the Handsome Sailor. Through the rose-tan of his complexion, , no pallor could have shown. It would have taken days of sequestration from the winds and the sun to have brought about the effacement of that, <pb facs="0ef9af5f-a02c-4cb4-8b2b-056d8929ab72" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16839"/>But the skeleton in the cheek-bone at the point of its angle was just beginning delicatly to be defined under the warm-tinted skin. In fervid hearts self-contained some brief experiences devour our human tissieu as secret fire in a ship&apos;s hold consumes cotton in the bale.  

</p><p>But now lying between the two guns, as nipped in the vice of fate,  Billy&apos;s agony, mainly proceeding from a generous young heart&apos;s virgin experience of the diabolical incarnate and effective in some men—the tension of that agony was over now. It survived not the something healing in the closeted interview with Captain Vere. <pb facs="e3b081cd-ad93-4c42-9935-8aa255a83d9f" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16841"/>Without movement, as in a trance. That adolescent expression previously noted as his, taking on something akin to the look of a slumbering child in the cradle when the warm hearth-glow of the still chamber at night plays on the dimples that at whiles mysteriously form in the cheek, silently coming and going there. For now and then in the gyved one&apos;s trance a serene happy light born of some wandering reminiscence <pb facs="eb0fb27c-1f67-41e1-8ef7-cdc05b663f50" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16511"/>or dream would diffuse itself over the his face, and then wane away only anew to return.  

</p><p>The Chaplain coming to see him and finding him thus, and percieving no  sign that he was conscious of his prescence, attentively regarded him for a space, then slipping aside, withdrew for the time, peradventure feeling that even he the minister of Christ tho&apos; receiving his stipend from Mars had no consolation to proffer which could result in a peace transcending that which he beheld. But in the small hours he came again. And the prisoner now awake to his surroundings noticed his approach <pb facs="a398d037-9f22-4f21-b96b-8ee8948463a3" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;16515"/>and civilly, all but cheerfully, welcomed him. But it was to little purpose that in the interview following the good man sought to bring Billy Budd to some godly understanding that he must die, and at dawn.  True, Billy himself freely referred to his death as a thing close near at hand; but it was something in the way that children will refer to death in general, who yet among their other sports will play a funeral with hearse and mourners. <pb facs="94fa4c33-e789-4f1b-8985-40c0bd7472a4" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17739"/>

</p><p>Not that like children Billy was incapable of conciving what death  really is. No, but he was wholly without irrational fear of it, a fear  more prevalent in highly civilized communities than those so-called   barbarous ones which in all respects stand nearer to unadulterate Nature. And, as elsewhere said, a barbarian Billy radically was; as much so, for all the costume, as his countrymen the British captives, living trophies, made to march in the Roman triumph of Germanicus. Quite as much so as those later barbarians, young men probably, and picked specimens among the <pb facs="0bef2806-0406-4faa-bbb1-a6a458bedffd" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17738"/>earlier British converts to Christianity, at least nominally such and taken to Rome (as to day converts from lesser isles of the sea may be taken to London) of whom the Pope of that time, admiring the strangness of their personal beauty so unlike the Italian stamp, their clear ruddy complexion and curled flaxen locks, exclaimed, &quot;Angles&quot; (meaning English the modern derivative) &quot;Angles do you call them? And is it because they look so like angels?&quot; Had it been later in time one would think that the Pope had in mind Fra Angelico&apos;s seraphs some of whom, plucking apples in gardens of the Hesperides <pb facs="6332c152-1f8d-409b-9664-6a5d7c1d02bd" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17737"/>have the faint rose-bud complexion of the more beautiful English girls.  

</p><p>If in vain the good Chaplain sought to impress the young barbarian with ideas of death akin to those conveyed in the skull, dial, and cross-bones on old tombstones; equally futile to all appearance were his efforts to bring home to him the thought of salvation and a Saviour. Billy listened, but less out of awe or reverence perhaps than from a certain natural politeness; doubtless at bottom regarding all that in much the same way that most mariners of his class take any discourse abstract or out of the common tone of the work-a-day world. <pb facs="b932f649-b30e-45be-9704-21f275a5d7ce" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17736"/>And this sailor-way of taking clerical discourse is not wholly unlike the way in which the primer pioneer of Christianity full of transcendent miracles was recieved long ago on tropic isles by any superior savage so called—a Tahitian say of Captain Cook&apos;s time or shortly after that time. Out of natural courtesy He recieved, but did not appropriate. It was like a gift placed in the palm of an outreached hand upon which the fingers do not close.  

</p><p>But the &quot;<hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi>&quot;s Chaplain was a discreet man possessing the good sense of a good heart. So he insisted not in his vocation here. At the insistance of Captain Vere, <pb facs="3fa696cb-bb5e-4f4a-9e2a-1c820e6c6443" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17734"/>a lieutenant had apprised him of pretty much everything as to Billy; and since he felt that innocence was even a better thing than religion  wherewith to go to Judgement, he reluctantly withdrew; but in his emotion not without first performing an act strange enough in an Englishman, and under the circumstances yet more so in any regular priest. Stooping over, he kissed on the fair cheek his fellow-man, a felon in martial law, one who though on the confines of death he felt he could never convert to a dogma; nor for all that did he fear for his future  

</p><p>Marvel not that having been made acquainted with the young sailor&apos;s essential innocense <pb facs="1ed013e1-55a1-4425-8db3-140851931234" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17732"/>the worthy man lifted not a finger to avert the doom of such a martyr to martial discipline. So to do would not only have been as idle as invoking the desert, but would also have been an audacious transgresson of the bounds of his function, one as exactly prescribed to him by military law as that of the boatswain or any other naval officer. Bluntly put, a chaplain is the minister of the Prince of Peace serving in the host of the God of War—Mars. As such, he is as incongruous as that musket of Beecher &amp;c at Christmas. Why then is he there? Because he indirectly subserves the purpose attested by the cannon; because too he lends the sanction of the religion of the meek to that which practically is the abrogation of everything but brute Force  </p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
