<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 27</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="1b23575c-2396-49ef-861b-5518d26137b9" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17640"/>
The silence at the moment of execution and for a moment or two  continuing thereafter, a silence but emphasized by the regular wash of the sea against the hull or the flutter of a sail caused by the helmsman&apos;s eyes being tempted astray, this emphasised silence was gradually was disturbed by a sound not easeily to be verbally rendered. Whoever has heard the freshet-wave of a torrent suddenly<pb facs="b6ca14c2-685f-431b-93d8-2fd13d945cb4" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17642"/>swelled by pouring showers in tropical mountains, showers not shared by the plain; whoever has heard the first muffled murmer of its sloping advance through precipitous woods, may form some conception of the sound now heard. The seeming remoteness of its source was because of its murmerous indistinctness since it came from close-by, even from the men massed on the ship&apos;s open deck. Being Inarticulate, it was dubious in significance further than it seemed to indicate some capricious revulsion of thought or feeling such as mobs <pb facs="c882968d-4dbf-4995-a567-a594192d0f1e" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17645"/>ashore are liable to, in the present instance possibly implying a sullen revocation on the men&apos;s part of their involuntary echoing of Billy&apos;s benediction. But ere the murmer had time to wax into clamor it was met by a stragetic command, the more telling that it came with abrupt unexpectedness:  

</p><p>&quot;Pipe down the starboard watch Boatswain, and see that they go.&quot;   

</p><p>Shrill as the shriek of the sea-hawk The silver whistles of the Boatswain and his mates pierced that ominous low sound, dissipating it; and <pb facs="a32d74db-3f52-4530-9979-960a33d5bcd1" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17659"/>yeilding to the mechanism of disipline the throng was thinned by one half. For the remainder most of them were set to temporary employments connected with trimming the yards and so forth, business readily to be got up to serve occasion by any officer-of-the-deck.   

</p><p>Now Each proceeding that follows a mortal sentence pronounced at sea  by a drum-head court is characterized by promptitude not perceptably merging into hurry, tho bordering that. The hammock, the one which had been Billy&apos;s bed when alive, having already been ballasted with shot and otherwise prepared <pb facs="b856a941-0819-48ea-b39b-ebf971893b41" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17660"/>to serve for his canvas coffin, the last office of the sea-undertakers, the Sail-Maker&apos;s Mates, were now speedily completed. When everything was in readiness, a second call for all hands made necessary by the unusual stragetic movement before mentioned was sounded and now to witness burial. 

</p><p>The details of this closing formality it needs not to give. But when the tilted plank let slide its freight into the sea, a second strange human murmer was heard, blended now with another inarticulate sound  proceeding from certain larger sea-fowl whose attention having been <pb facs="98dff69b-6a19-4341-aff0-5fb755baeb4f" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17663"/>attracted by the peculiar commotion in the water resulting from the heavy sloped dive of the shotted hammock into the sea flew screaming to the spot. So near the hull did they come, that the stridor or bony creak of their gaunt double-jointed pinions was audible. As the ship under light airs passed on, leaving the burial-spot astern, they still kept circling it low down with the moving shadow of their outstretchd wings and the croaked requiem of their cries.

</p><p>Upon sailors as superstitious as those of the age preceeding ours, men-of war&apos;s men too who had just <pb facs="6b187cc3-f677-42db-b60f-3fc2c768682b" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17664"/>beheld the prodigy of repose in the form suspended in air, and now foundering in the deeps; to such mariners the action of the sea-fowl tho&apos; dictated by mere animal greed for prey, was big with no prosaic significance. An uncertain movement began among them, in which some encroachment was made. It was tolerated but for a moment. For suddenly the drum beat to quarters, which familiar sound happening at least twice every day, had upon the present occasion a signal peremptoriness  in it. True martial discipline long continued superinduces in average man a sort of impulse docility whose operation at the official word of command much resembles in its promptitude the effect of an instinct. <pb facs="f928ade0-7618-4faf-85c1-b28bd28f7654" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17665"/>
The drum-beat dissolved the multitude, distributing most of them along the batteris of the two covered gun-decks. There, as wont, the guns&apos; crews stood by their respective cannon erect and silent. In due course the First Officer, sword under arm and standng in his place on the quarter-deck formally recieved the successive reports of the sworded Lieutenants commanding the sections of batteries below; the last of which reports being made the summed report he delivered with the customary salute to the Commander. All this occupied time, which in the present case, was the object in beating to quarters at an <pb facs="44f112d4-2272-42fe-b44c-3c4aa3e8e2f3" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17666"/>hour prior to the customary one. That such variance from usage was  authorized by an officer like Captain Vere, a martinet as some deemed him, was evidence of the necessity for unusual action implyed in what he deemed to be temporarily the mood of his men. &quot;With mankind&quot; he would say &quot;forms, measured forms are everything; and that is the import couched in the story of Orpheus, with his lyre spell-binding the wild denizens of the wood.&quot; And this he once applied to the disruption of forms going on across the Channel and the consequces thereof.  

</p><p>At this unwonted muster at quarters, all proceeded as at the regular hour. The band on the quarter-deck played a sacred air. After which the Chaplain went thro&apos; <pb facs="4fb85ecc-9556-43f1-a4c2-860dce114ef7" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17667"/>the customary morning service. That done, the drum beat the retreat; and toned by music and religious rites subserving the discipline <reg originalText="&amp;">and</reg> purposes of war, the men in their wonted orderly manner, dispersed to the places allotted them when not at the guns.

</p><p>And now it was full day. The fleece of low-hanging vapor had vanished, licked up by the sun that late had so glorified it. And the circumambient air in the clearness of its serenity was like smooth  white marble in the polished block not yet removed from the marble-dealer&apos;s yard.</p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
