<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 29</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="c64044e4-1a37-4dc6-abeb-c073c461fcc4" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;18724"/>
Some few weeks after the execution, among other matters under the head of <hi rend="italic">News</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Mediterranean</hi>, there appeared in a naval Chronicle of the time, an authorized weekly publication an account of the affair. It was doubtless for the most part written in good faith, tho&apos; the medium, partly rumor, through which the facts must have reached the writer, served to deflect and in part falsify them. The account was as follows:—

</p><p>&quot;On the tenth of the last month a deplorable occurence took <pb facs="c7ee78b9-73d6-4655-917f-bcdb571ca07b" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17615"/>place on board H. M. S. <hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi>. John Claggart, the ship&apos;s master-at-arms, discovering that some sort of plot was incipient among an inferior section of the ship&apos;s company, and that the ringleader was one William Budd; he, Claggart in the act of arraigning the man before the Captain was vindictivly stabbed to the heart by the suddenly drawn sheath-knife of Budd.

</p><p>The deed and the implement employed, sufficiently suggest that tho&apos; mustered into the service under an English name the assasin was no Englishman, but one of those aliens adopting English cognomens whom <pb facs="c0f528f4-a925-4476-8052-eada42cc0ffe" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17616"/>the present extraordinary necessities of the service have caused to be admitted into it in considerable numbers 

</p><p>The enormity of the crime and the extreme depravity of the criminal, appear the greater in view of the character of the victim, a middle-aged man respectable, and discreet, belonging to that minor official grade, the petty-officers, upon whom, as none know better than the commissioned gentlemen, the efficiency of His Majesty&apos;s navy so largely depends. His function was an responsible one; at once onerous <reg originalText="&amp;">and</reg> thankless and his fidelity in it the <pb facs="e7ebfaab-8c56-406d-a6ad-933eb8681840" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17617"/>greater because of his strong patriotic  impulse. In this instance as in so many other instances in these days, the character of this unfortunate man signally refutes, if refutation were needed, that peevish saying attributed to the late Dr. Johnson, that patriotism is  the last refuge of a scoundrel.  

</p><p>The criminal paid the  penalty of his crime. The promptitude of the punishment has proved salutary. Nothing amiss is now apprehended aboard H. M. S. <hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi>.&quot;  

</p><p>The above appearing in a publication now <pb facs="f11f885d-e903-493e-b804-3bc2a9841b99" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;"/>long ago superannuated and forgotten is all that hitherto has stood in human record to attest what manner of men respectively were John Claggart and Billy Budd. </p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
