<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 7</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="1445d88b-921a-4215-bf4b-0ecb6fa776dd" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15622"/>
In view of the past that the Commander of the <hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi> plays in scenes shortly to follow, it may be well to fill out that sketch of him outlined in the previous chapter. 

</p><p>Aside from his qualities as a sea-officer Captain Vere was an exceptional character. Unlike no few of England&apos;s renowned sailors, long and arduous service with signal devotion to it, had not resulted in absorbing and salting the entire man. He had a marked leaning <pb facs="51350eda-0413-4d7a-97b8-b36c001b84af" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15623"/>toward everything intellectual. He loved books, never going to sea without a newly replenished library, compact but of the best. The isolated leisure, in some cases so wearisome, falling at intervals to commanders even during a war-cruise, never was  tedious to Captain Vere. With nothing of that literary taste which less heeds the thing conveyed than the vehicle, his bias was toward those books to which every serious mind of superior order occupying any active post of authority in the world, naturally inclines: books treating of actual men and events no matter of what era—history, biography and <pb facs="4a8dc46e-0a1b-4070-95ed-6219a8768b2b" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15637"/>unconventional writers like Montaigne, who, free from cant and convention, honestly and in the spirit of common sense philosophize upon realities.       <pb facs="dfbbaf54-a3af-40d4-9b73-6b7b6265531f" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15638"/>In this line of reading he found confirmation of his own more reserved thoughts—confirmation which he had vainly sought in social converse, so that as touching most fundamental topics, there had got to be established in him some positive convictions, which he forefelt would abide in him essentially unmodified so long as his intelligent part remained unimpaired. In view of the troubled period in which his lot was cast, this was well for him. His settled convictions were as a dyke against those <pb facs="26aa4fe4-dc53-4036-bce5-0a9680664eb2" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15642"/>as invading waters of novel opinion social political and otherwise, which carried away as in a no few minds in those days, minds by nature not inferior to his own. While other members of that aristocracy to which by birth he belonged were incensed at the innovaters mainly because their theories were inimical to the privileged classes, Captain Vere disinterestedly disinterestedly oppposed <pb facs="d1a9d83d-7bde-41be-a4e9-c3ccb083834d" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15640"/>them not alone because they seem to him in susceptible of embodiment in lasting institutions, but at war with the peace of the world and the true welfare of mankind. <pb facs="c75f0ffb-9690-46a8-b6d7-54453fc4e19b" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15628"/>

</p><p>With minds less stored than his and less earnest, some officers of his rank, with whom at times he would necessarily consort, found him lacking in the companionable quality, a dry and bookish gentleman, as they deemed. Upon any chance withdrawal from their company one would be  <pb facs="5de536e7-7ed9-4cd4-aaa6-a8242b96b9fc" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15629"/>apt to say to another, something like this: &quot;Vere is a noble fellow,. Spite the gazzettes, Sir Horatio meaning him who beca Lord Nels is at bottom scarse a better seaman or fighter. But between you and me now do&apos;nt you think there is a queer streak of the pedantic running thro&apos; him? Yes, like the King&apos;s yarn in a coil of navy-rope? 

</p><p>Some apparent ground there was for This sort of confidential criticism; since not only did the Captain&apos;s discourse never fall into the jocosely familiar, but in illustrating of any point touching the stirring personages <pb facs="9a2076a0-a629-4ae8-b95b-95102f00f029" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15651"/>and events of the time he would be as apt to cite some historic character or incident of antiquity as that he would cite from the moderns. He seemed <pb facs="4716aa29-efce-4606-896b-dfa732ba049d" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;15631"/>unmindful of the circumstance that to his bluff company such remote allusions however pertinent they might really be were altogether alien to men whose reading was mainly confined to the journals. But  considerateness in such matters is not easy to natures constituted like Captain Vere&apos;s. Their honesty prescribes to them directness, sometimes far-reaching like that of a migratory fowl that in its flight never heeds when it crosses a frontier.</p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
