<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
	 		<titleStmt>
				<title>Billy in the Darbies</title>
	 		</titleStmt>
	 		<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<pubPlace></pubPlace>
				<date></date>
				<authority></authority>
			   <availability>
			      <p></p> 
				</availability>
		   </publicationStmt>
	 		<sourceDesc>
	 	      <p></p>
	 		</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text>
	<body><p><pb facs="2175daa7-5ff4-4513-a533-524116c4179a" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17619"/>
Good of the Chaplain to enter Lone Bay  
And down on his marrow-bones here and pray  
For the likes just o&apos; me, Billy Budd.—But, look:  
Through the port comes the moon-shine astray!  
It tips the guard&apos;s cutlas and silvers this nook;  
But &apos;twill die in the dawning of Billy&apos;s last day.   
A jewel-block they&apos;ll make of me tomorrow,   
Pendant pearl from the yard-arm-end  
Like the ear-drop I gave to Bristol Molly— <pb facs="1f5f7b5f-9701-44f9-a612-7952c8780796" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17622"/>
O, &apos;tis me, not the sentence they&apos;ll suspend.  
Ay, Ay, all is up; and I must up too  
Early in the morning, aloft from alow.
On an empty stomach now never it would do.   
They&apos;ll give me a nibble—bit o&apos; buiscit ere I go.  
Sure, a messmate will reach me the last parting cup;
But turning heads away from the hoist and the belay,  
Heaven knows who will have the running of me up!
No pipe to those halyards—But aren&apos;t it all sham?
A blur&apos;s in my eyes; it is dreaming that I am.  
A hatchet to my hauzer? all adrift to go? <pb facs="b8634be2-7a85-47ba-b68b-83ccbcb32e53" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17621"/>
The drum roll to grog, and Billy never know?
But Donald he has promised to stand by the plank;
So I&apos;ll shake a friendly hand ere I sink.
But—no! It is dead then I&apos;ll be, come to think.—
I remember Taff the Welshman when he sank.
And his cheek it was like the budding pink
But me they&apos;ll lash me in hammock, drop me deep. <pb facs="7c8052db-ab15-410e-a1ac-3faa69cce0c9" tl_leaf="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;app.textlab.org&#x2F;transcriptions&#x2F;17620"/>
Fathoms down, fathoms down, how I&apos;ll dream fast asleep.  
I feel it stealing now. Sentry, are you there? 
Just ease this darbies at the wrist, 
and roll me over fair,  
I am sleepy, and the oozy weeds about me twist.</p></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
